Guide to the Gertrude Barnstone papers, 1956 - 2015 MS 587
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Gertrude Barnstone papers
1956-2015
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Barnstone, Gertrude
MS 587
5 Linear Feet (6 boxes)
This collection contains the personal files of native Houstonian Gertrude Barnstone, including information on her careers in politics, social activism, education, and art. In addition to newsclippings, magazines, programs, invitations, and posters, the collection also contains numerous photographs of her sculptures and her personal sketchbooks.
Biographical Sketch
Gertrude Barnstone was born in Houston, Texas on September 5, 1925. She received a Bachelor of Arts in English from Rice University in 1945 and also studied art at the Houston Museum of Fine Arts and Stanford University Art Department. In 1953, Gertrude Barnstone was comissioned to create a sculpture of two large, curved aluminum pieces for the exterior of the U.S. Green Stamp building in Houston. She continued to contribute artwork to local exhibitions as well as create sculptures for private residences, working largely with steel, but also with wire, glass, mirrors, fabric, and other materials.
In the 1960s and 1970s Gertrude Barnstone took an active role in politics and social activism, championing women's rights and civil rights. She was elected to the Houston Independent School District School Board in 1964 and served a five-year term while achieving significant changes regarding desegregation and federal aid.
In 1969 Gertrude Barnstone divorced from her husband of thirteen years, Howard Barnstone, a prominent architect and co-designer of the Rothko Chapel. She began studying welding at Houston Community College in 1969 and worked at a factory making plexiglass skylights in help support her three children, a job that also provided the inspiration to incorporate glass into her colorful and intricate metal sculptures. From 1970-1973 Gertrude Barnstone was producer of the KPRC-TV educational children's program "Sundown's Treehouse" and from 1972-1973 served as Director of Development for the Institute for Storm Research, focusing on minority needs and representation in both positions. Although her 1972 campaign for a seat in the State Senate, District 15 was unsuccessful, she remained dedicated to building a stronger community, serving as President and treasurer for the Texas ACLU Foundation, President of the National Coalition of Women's Art Organization, 1981-1982, and president of the Houston Women's Caucus for Art, 1980. In the early 1990s she founded Artist Rescue Mission, an organization that provided aid to the people in war-torn Sarajevo. In 1995, Barnstone received the Lifetime Achievement in Civil Liberties award from the Greater Houston chapter of the ACLU.
Gertrude Barnstone continues to create distinct glass and steel sculptures ranging from floor lamps, to tables, to abstract outdoor scultpures for both private and public spaces.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains the personal files of native Houstonian Gertrude Barnstone, including information on her careers in politics, social activism, education, and art.
Series I includes newsclippings, brochures, reports, campaign realia, and other materials related to Barnstone's involvement in local, state, and national politics.
Series II primarily includes materials related to Barnstone's activism during her five year tenure on the HISD School Board from 1964-1969 and her role as producer of the educational children's program "Sundown's Treehouse" from 1970-1973. Included are brochures, newsclippings, articles, awards, scripts, and other materials.
Series III is divided into three subseries. Subseries A contains general files on Gertrude Barnstone's career in art and the Houston art community, including newsclippings, exhibition invitations and programs, awards, correspondence, and other materials. Subseries B contains photographs of Barnstone sculptures spanning her entire career as well as photographs of Barnstone herself and documentation of events at which she was honored for her diverse pursuits. Subseries C contains her personal sketchbooks and loose sketches of ink drawings and watercolors. Likewise, the oversize materials consist of sketchbooks and loose drawings, as well as campaign posters, photographs and magazines.
Access Restrictions
This material is open for research.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored offsite at the Library Service Center and require 24-hour notice for retrieval. Please contact the Woodson Research Center at 713-348-2586 or woodson@rice.edu for more information.
Acquisition Information
Donated by Gertrude Barnstone, October 10, 2011.
Index Terms
Subjects
Women; Women -- Political activity; Arts -- Texas; Art; Politics and government
- Series I: Politics & Activism, 1965-2006; 157818
  - Texas State and National Governments, 1965-76; no date; 157951 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Texas State Senator campaign, 1972; 157952 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Houston environment, 1972-2006; 157953 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "A Texan in Washington" radio show demo tape (5" reel), 1975; 157954 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Southern Africa Task Force, 1983; 157955 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Texas State Legislature Nicaragua visit, 1984; 157956 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Newsclippings - Politics and goverment, 157957 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Newsclippings - Barnstone family, 157958 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Series II: Education, 1956-1973; 157819
  - African Americans and educational theatre, 1956-66; 157959 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - NEA Conferences on Faculty Desegregation, 1966; 157960 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Awards, 1969; 157961 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Children's programs, 1973; 157962 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - "Sundown's Treehouse", 157963 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - "Sundown's Treehouse" scripts, 157964 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - "Sundown's Treehouse" ideas, 157974 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Association for Educational Communications & Technology, 157975 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - The International University of Communications, n.d.; 157976 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Series III: Art, 1975-2015; 157820
  - Subseries A: General Files, 1975-2015; 157822
    - Programs and brochures, 1975-88; 157983 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Proposal drafts, 1976-80; 157998 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Main Street Art Festival, 1976; 157999 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Houston Door Show, 1979; 158000 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - "Women in Sight: New Art in Texas", 1979-80; 158001 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Made in Houston show, 1980; 158002 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Individual income tax return, 1981; 158003 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Midtown Art Center, 1984-85; 158004 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Awards, 1986-2010; 158005 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - The SPARK Program, 1991-93; 158017 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Seaside, Florida, 1993; 158018 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Artist Rescue Mission, 1994-2007; 158019 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Vivian Ayers, 1998; 158020 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - The American Institute of Architects, Houston, 2002; 158021 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Cyclandic art, 2005; 158022 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - "Dangerous Hands", 158023 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Radio dramas, n.d.; 158024 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Vita, 158025 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Art exhibition invitations and programs, 158026 (Box 2, Folder 19-20)
    - Newsclippings - Art, 158027 (Box 2, Folder 21-22)
    - Newsclippings and Programs - Theatrical (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Newsclippings - General (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Paint brushes and drawing ink, 158028 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Correspondence (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Oral History, 2015 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Subseries B: Photographs, 157823
    - ACLU Lifetime Achievement Award celebration scrapbook, 1995; 158029 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - The Association of Rice Alumni Honors Dinner, 1999; 158030 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Metal and glass tree sculpture for Jim & Lynn Parsons, 2008-09; 158031 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Gertrude Barnstone, 158032 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Sculptures, 158033 (Box 3, Folder 5-9)
    - Miscellaneous, 158034 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Slides and negatives: Metalwork sculptures, 158035 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Subseries C: Sketches, 157824
    - Sketchbooks, n.d.; 158036 (Box 4, Folder 1-6)
    - Loose sketches, n.d.; 158037 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Series IV: Oversize, 1964-2007; 157821
  - Sketchbooks (11" x 14"), n.d.; 158038 (Box 5)
  - Photographs: Scupltures, n.d.; 158039 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Photographs: US Green Stamp Corp. sculpture, n.d.; 158040 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Art show programs, 1976; 1984; 158041 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Magazines, 1965-2007; 158042 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Color photograph Gertrude Barnstone and Houston Independent School District Board, 158043 (Map-drawer 141)
  - Three sketches on posterboard with colored charcoal [fountain?], n.d.; 158044 (Map-drawer 141)
  - Poster: Gertrude Barnstone for State Senate, 15, n.d.; 158045 (Map-drawer 141)
  - Poster: Gertrude Barnstone, Amnesty International, n.d.; 158046 (Map-drawer 141)
  - Oversize color photograph, Gertrude Barnstone, n.d.; 158047 (Map-drawer 141)
  - Two black & white photographs of Gertrude Barnstone "Vote Nov. 6", n.d.; 158048 (Map-drawer 141)
  - Color photograph of Gertrude Barnstone printed on paper, n.d.; 158049 (Map-drawer 141)
  - Mayoral proclamation "A Day for Sarajevo." Signed by Bob Lanier, Mayor of the City of Houston., April 13, 1995; 158050 (Map-drawer 141)
  - Certificate of appreciation for Gertrude Barnstone. Board of Directors, Houston Independent School District., December 15, 1969; 158051 (Map-drawer 141)
  - Laminated newspaper article, "..Not here, says Mrs. Barnstone." Houston Chronicle., April 18, 1965; 158052 (Map-drawer 141)
  - Poster: Gertrude Barnstone. Painting, Sculpture, Drawings. The Louisiana Gallery., April 18, 1964; 158053 (Map-drawer 141)
  - Two nude watercolors. (Removed from frames)., n.d.; 158054 (Map-drawer 141)
  - Oversized nude sketch in mat board, n.d.; 158055 (Map-drawer 141)
  - Various sketches, posters, charcoal and ink drawings (50+), 158056 (Map-drawer 141)
  - U.S. Green Stamp Bldg. Poster with photographs of aluminum bent bar and tubing sculpture by Gertrude Barnstone, 158057 (Map-drawer 141)
  - Color photographs of sculpture mounted on two pieces of foamboard., n.d.; 158058 (Map-drawer 142)
- Series V: Digital files
  - Interview of Gertrude Barnstone, by Randy Tibbits, Sunday August 25, 2013, discussing Margo Jones and the Houston Community Players
  - Gertrude Barnstone: Home Movies
    Related Materials
    The Fondren Library general collection has a DVD copy of this video. F394.H853 B37 2015